hello and welcome this is active
bookstream number
001.06 on governing continuous
transformation it's January 17 2023 off
to you blue
to a participatory online Institute that
is communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference these are all
of our social media links when you where
you can find us if you're looking for us
outside the industry this is a recorded
and an archived live stream so please
provide us with feedback so that we can
improve on our work all backgrounds and
perspectives are welcome here and we
will be trying to follow a good video
etiquette for live streams other than my
cat who feels free to interrupt whenever
she sees fit
um you can reach out to us if you would
like to get involved with any of our
ongoing projects or live streams or
propose a new project
and today we are going to discuss uh
this is bookstream number
001.06 so this is our sixth
contextualization video or the
contextualization video over chapter six
um and we are going to study governing
continuous transformation reframing the
strategy governance conversation by
Bijan kesri who was nice enough to join
us and discuss some of his ideas with us
last week this video is just an
introduction to some of the ideas
presented in the book it's not in a
review or a final word in any way so
we're just going to Jump Right In
um and introduce ourselves so I am blue
I am a researcher in New Mexico and I
will pass it off to Daniel
I'm Daniel I'm a researcher in
California and
looking forward to the continuation of
the series Tyler
hey my name is Tyler I'm a practitioner
not a researcher so I lead product and
protocol design at 4K protocol and I
also do governance on the limits of Dow
tooling with medigo all right blue
awesome
So today we're going to get into uh part
two of the book so free energy
governance and we're going to discuss
the first chapter in part two
um okay
so part two free energy governments and
we're discussing chapter six and there's
kind of two sections and actually Jean
broke chapter six for us so there's two
sections of chapter six the upper
echelon View and the predictive
processing framework
um and and here just a little intro to
part two free energy governance
um says free energy governance
introduces a novel cross-hiorical
generative framework that uniquely
applies the triplet of structure
cognition and capabilities as the
building blocks of the firm's generative
model specifically in the context of
continuous strategic renewal in
distributed and discontinuous Market
environments essentially six core
theoretical perspectives together lay
the foundation for this new conversation
structure upper echelon View and
prediction processing framework
um so that's what we're going to discuss
today and then I'm assuming that the
next chapter is going forward are going
to focus on cognition which encompasses
attention-based View and an activist
approach and capabilities encompassing
Dynamic capability View and antagonistic
neural networks perspectives
structure cognition and capabilities
form one integrated system under free
energy governance failure in any one
domain is likely to challenge firm
survival the framework's core
propositions outlined at the end of this
chapter summarize free energy
governance's ambition for a practice
relevant theoretical contribution as
both the generative logic of
organizational governance as well as an
early warning system predicting
corporate decay
um so Tyler do you want to jump in and
read the absolute abstracts here
View and prediction processing framework
address free energy governance
structural Dimension indeed upper
echelon is the size strategic decision
making however
uev suffers from several limitations
there's no explicit consideration for
the board of directors and the language
between the upper echelon and to the
rest of the organization I.E the
coupling of governance and operational
challenges is unidirectionally top down
and therefore at best and complete how
the field data can systematically talk
to Upper Echelon and influence their
values procession and attention remains
of black bugs it's prediction processing
framework Embraces structure more
holistically addressing the hierarchical
disconnect and more importantly the
circular causality between top down
predictions and Bottoms Up stimuli
I don't know just the second part here
dissonance bearing messages
sorry
dissonance pairing messages occur at the
firm stimuli level bottom close to its
resource markets long before top
leadership has any sense of a living
challenge prediction processing
framework is determined by three
categorical imperatives first upper
echelon's production models and
predictions must be explainable second
each of the hierarchical layers must
have formal and informal
interfaces coupling each layer to the
next layer and third the firm's
generative model is the firm's Eco Niche
prediction processing framework provides
an entirely New Perspective and language
embracing strategic renewal as a matter
of bottom-up top-down prediction error
minimization not least setting 3 the
full potential of the human machine
interface I mean it's interesting here
like
I wonder what he means by human machine
interface like humans as a functioning
machine like um as an organism maybe or
as like a
um
I I don't know or like directly like the
human computer interaction like how we
interface with our technology so I I was
curious like this I found this human
machine interface
um Clause kind of like threw me for a
Loops a little bit you guys know any
comments
imagines a world where like you're very
tied in with the the AI and I personally
haven't like witnessed this myself like
being in an organization where like
that's like a seamless integration where
like you might use like a machine
learning framework but rather that like
it is like a dialogue between the the
frame ml model and then the human I
think that's what he's kind of imagining
um but I think it's a little bit unclear
I think you're right blue
so like I've I've like studied and taken
like courses and intelligence with
people who study like their course of
study is like human computer interaction
like the interface between humans and
machines and like it's always like
um you know that there are topics of
study are very different than
um like thinking about themselves as a
firm right right like they they think
about like their their topical study
like interacting with like a wellness
robot like you've seen like the health
like little robot you know for elderly
people that like checks up on them and
it you know it's like the how how do
elderly people best interact with
computers and children and they have a
very different level of interaction both
like the older generation and kids they
have different ways to interact and
interface with um computers and like
they do it best in an embodied kind of
machine which I found super interesting
like where you know in the mid-range we
can just talk to the we have no problem
talking to Alexa and it could just be
like a microchip like speaker in the
wall and it would be be a big deal but
like they want something in a teddy bear
or some kind of like machine that that
like looks has a face or something like
that and they interact with it in a much
different way much much more efficiently
actually so I found that super
interesting but this is what I think
about when I think about the human
machine interface is like the actual
like Markov boundary right like between
humans and machines and and so like what
is the potential of a Markov boundary I
don't know anyway so sorry I'm rambling
um okay so just a few keywords here
upper echelon view prediction processing
framework we'll go back and revisit it
double learning look into optimization
organizational sense making and um I
think the the biggest chunk of new
information that Bijan brought into this
chapter what were these habits of mind
um okay so do you want to read this for
me Tyler upper echelon View
cool so uev defines the organization as
a reflection of its upper echelon the
I.E its top management team UAV Central
premise is that Executives experiences
values and personalities affect their
field of vision their one field of
vision the directors they look and
listen select a perception what they
actually see in here and three
interpretation how they attach meaning
to what they see in here so essentially
UE Embraces sensing and sense making not
only as an essential leadership
qualities but as a foundation for
strategic choices and firm performance
cool and so there are a couple claims
kind of associated with this upper
echelon View
um Bijan says however upper Ashland view
suffers from several limitations in
particular there is no explicit
consideration for the board of directors
as part of the upper echelon the many
dimensions by which a non-executive
chairman relates to the CEO for example
are likely to determine strategic
choices he goes on to say
um well upper echelon view has neglected
the board of directors free energy
governance emphasizes the importance of
the board as part of a firm's upper
echelon top management tier and the
board of directors here jointly labor
labeled as the upper echelon are
together the locus of strategic decision
making more importantly the board of
directors can potentially assume a
unique cognitive role and strategy
process in the form of dynamic board
capabilities that is highly
complementary to that of senior
executive leadership strategic capacity
and I was wondering Tyler maybe if you
have any comments here on like you know
normally the board is not included as
the upper echelon and bishan is like
making the case for their inclusion is
that typical in like organizations or
what you think uh no that that's not
common and I think John like touched on
this in our last call with him the last
discussion is that like usually you see
the board as more of like a sounding
board as that there are a they give a
final sign off a rubber stamp they make
sure you're not doing anything totally
illegal and irresponsible but they're
not really there to like really be in
the weeds with you uh whereas what Bajan
is arguing is like no actually like they
have by by virtue of being kind of
separate from the day-to-day work they
can give you a more unbiased view of
like what you should be doing
strategically like the capabilities you
should be building and that they
actually are like a really integral part
of your whole strategic process and so
it's unusual to think of them as like
these two like really critical halves
usually people think of the board as
this like nuisance that they have to
appease not as like a real thing that
can actually add value to the
organization
absolutely thank you for that input
um okay so a couple more things to say
about UAV and we just kind of excerpt it
from the text
um upper echelon view is far too
restrictive and one-sided top-down to
explain through the lens of leadership
qualities the anatomy of success and
failure of strategic renewal this book
invites to a new stream of upper echelon
youth Centric research that
operationalize upper echelon View's
impact on current performance not so
much in terms of antecedents and
consequences of Team diversity but as a
function of structure cognitively public
governance and operational channels in
the form of top down bottom-up circular
prediction error minimization second
cognition embracing environment as a
matter of action-centric enactment and
third capabilities developing Duality
management as a dynamic board capability
to rewire the plane while flying it
um he goes on to say the prediction
processing framework allows us to
embrace structure more holistically
I don't know if you guys have any
comments here
yeah
let's just say that we're in a
tripartite firm with the upper echelon
consisting of the higher management and
or the board of directors middle
management and then the front lines as
Vision mentioned last week
overly emphasizing in a given Eco Niche
any one of those three sections is going
to lead to maladaptive decision making
and implementation
so the question that I see these
repeated structure cognition
capabilities returning to is about
striking and adaptive balance
amongst
the upper echelon
the middle management implementational
layers and the front line day-to-day
experience just like the body and the
organism strike a balance between the
primary perceptual organs the
intermediate processing and then the
central processing
well thank you
all right so moving on to the prediction
processing framework
um Tyler do you want to read this for us
do you mind all right so neither
governance or strategic strategic
renewal research has addressed the
hierarchical disconnect of the top down
bottom-up circular causality sir then
acceptable contributions aside
uh ppf opens the pro perceptual black
box of how shared meaning and
expectations are constructed and
optimized and pursued optimizing the
performance sustainability of strategic
renewal in management science PBS
episode logical Origins can be traced to
Argus agaris's theory of action
perspective specifically the concept of
double Loop learning defined as a form
of learning that challenges the existing
routines and Status Quo action-centric
learnings at the heart of cross-cycle
prediction processing framework there's
a need for fundamentally for a
fundamentally new organizing framework
systems preparedness to unlearn Powers
the receptivity the corrective feedback
of the decision-making unit and hence is
critical to ppf's top-down bottom-up
learning prediction error immunization
challenge
well Daniel do you have any comments
here yes
um in Bayesian learning
learning really is on learning you have
to move the distribution around and so
Bayesian learning isn't just throwing
more papers onto a stack or onto a
knowledge pile but when we have to
update How likely we think things are
that isn't unlearning so it's
interesting to see how it's connected
here to like openness to the unknown
negative capabilities and the way in
which in the single Loop which I know
we'll get to you can Implement and do
local maximization and maybe be locally
adaptive but if we really want to pull
back and amidst these discontinuities
continue to find success then we need to
engage in that kind of double Loop
learning
you totally took the words out of my
mouth and actually just said it so much
better so um I I also was like really
reminded of Bayesian learning here with
with unlearning because like for all the
reasons you just stated
um okay so double Loop learning just to
revisit I think we talked about this
maybe not last week with bijanpa just a
couple weeks ago
um so double Loop learning occurs when
in order to correct an error it's
necessary to alter the governing values
of the master programs so in this little
figure it's just like single Loop
learning is actions and that's the
consequences actions assess the
consequences where the double Loop
learning zooms out to kind of see like
what governing variables influence the
actions that that are being taken
um so it's kind of like the the setback
in a hierarchical control model
um and Bijan says that we need error
feedback loops to adjust predictions and
more importantly to eventually update
prediction models
um AKA double Loop learning
okay so the Jean goes on to make the
claim he says upper echelon Remains the
centralized purveyor of predictions as
well as Trustee of prediction models
hence the prediction processing powered
free energy governance framework is
distributed at the bottom but
centralized at the top however for
prediction error minimization to work
each hierarchical layer must be
dedicated to one simple first order
principle minimize free energy to
minimize error and surprise consequently
prediction models will generatively
evolve by way of self-learning this is
the essence of unsupervised
self-organization
um any comments here
sure so in terms of communication what
are these different parts of the um what
are the different parts of the
organization or organism sharing with
each other
so they might just be representing what
they are perceiving like everyone is
just filling others in on what they're
getting so that's one imperative is just
unbiased pass through a communication
um another
imperative might be give the other
person what they expect so here the
management is saying we expect that
you're going to sell 10 cars and then
the front line says yes we sold 10 cars
um
where
free energy minimization as a way to
minimize or bound error and surprise
comes in is that it says actually the
communication imperative shouldn't be
simple pass-through and it also
shouldn't be conformist but rather what
is communicated should provide
information about to what extent
the expectations of your communicating
partner are being violated so if they
say we expect 10 cars the minimum
communication might just be yes if
that's true
and then maybe there's um a dial that
can be turned depending on whether it's
fewer than that or more than that
and so that puts communication into an
interesting setting where we're explicit
about what the in this case top down
predictions are and then we situate the
bottom up communication as reflecting
the adequacy of those expectations
rather than just being plain
pass-through or conformist
yeah just to build on that a little bit
because in my experience like there's
like like you sit down like two kinds of
communication there's one of like very
clear like hey this is what we're
expecting did you meet that like a very
clear prediction and there's another one
that's more just like dissonance like
things just like aren't working well and
people don't fully understand why and
this is my experience like really trying
to communicate in a very like clear
linear way like through each stack of
the hierarchy
uh about like trying to warn someone of
a of an issue for example or communicate
like the new world or new like how you
should update your generative model that
tends to not work nearly as well as just
things not working well and people
bumping up against uh discontinuities
and dissonance themselves and people
really like oh there's like a problem in
the system this is a signal that we need
to fix it and usually that's in my
experience like how communication
happens between hierarchies and it feels
really bad and it feels very chaotic but
at the end of the day I think that's how
like the organism of the firm processes
information
yeah it's asking too much for the skin
cell to provide a situational report on
the wound all it can and must do is
report a difference from expectation
that gets clustered with other incoming
sensory modalities and integrated by the
upper echelon to make a decision about
okay now we're going to get a Band-Aid
so understanding that the skin cell is
not going to tell you to get a Band-Aid
but also the Band-Aid decision-making
unit isn't going to have direct access
to the skin
cannot be implemented at the firm level
how like that that coupling between
different different layers of the
hierarchy man can I talk today the
coupling between the different layers of
the hierarchy how should that work so
like just for example like the skin cell
doesn't necessarily need to know what is
happening in the liver right like it's
not like a direct coupling there
um and and so how how do you selectively
choose like it as like a management like
what to communicate down the chain like
if I'm in the upper echelon like what
does the board communicate to the top
management here what is the top
management tier then communicate like
Downstream and how do you filter that
information so that it's like like how
do you like prioritize salience here and
just
um not like open up a fire hose like
here's all the information because
that's not like effective for
communicating but it also like you like
that disconnect like any kind of
filtering can lead to like a level of
Disconnect that's maybe unwanted so how
do you like prioritize that information
flow
um down layers of the hierarchy and like
I um always am interested in this so
like whether it's biological or
organizational
I have a couple examples to like
illustrate that so for example I worked
at a company called actually I won't
name any names here but it was a tech
company and it was like a very it was
probably like 400 people and it was like
structured very hierarchically and so
basically from the bottom bottom rungs
to the top you would have each person
would report up to their unit and have
like hey this is what we did these are
like risks you should be aware of right
and this would happen on a weekly basis
and then that would get bubbled up into
the next running out of hierarchy which
would be it keeps getting synthesized
and refined at each level of the
hierarchy until you get up to like the
CEO right which is presume like
ostensibly like uh condensing all this
information from 400 people up to like
one report but the CEO gets of like five
bullets of takeaways right and so like
what happens like in Bajan even talks
about this in the chapter is that like
it gets so filtered by that point and
also each rung in a hierarchy has like
their own incentives and things that
they're trying to like politically
maximize for that becomes like not even
that useful so what
what's a lot more useful though is when
things uh well I guess two things one is
if things go wrong like say there's a
bug in the app and something needs a
firing to be put out right away that's
information that skips or all the wrongs
and goes straight to the CEO another one
is when people would a lot of times
Executives would schedule meetings but
just random people in the organization
so you'd have like an executive who's
like the CFO would schedule a meeting
with some engineer and just to like
basically cross the chasm of all the
different levels of the hierarchy just
be like hey like what's going on like
tell me like what you perceive the
problems to be in your sub unit and
that's a way for them to kind of get
like this unfiltered view of like random
people like by sampling random people
across the organization so I think
they're like ways you can do this but
yeah it's really it's really difficult
foreign
okay so moving on we'll talk a little
bit about optimization and um I just
yeah put up here like the um you know
distributed versus
um hierarchical
um
levels the networks
um okay so Bijan says the challenge is
not only one of building interferm
connections between upper echelons
top-down predictions and field
Management's bottom-up stimuli but
optimizing the top-down bottom-up
process within each and every layer of
the hierarchy
why am I fixing that of the hierarchy in
form of feedback connections
optimization is Central to prediction
processing framework this optimization
makes every level in the hierarchy
accountable to others while the
generative sense making processes and
capabilities are critical performance
element at every level of the hierarchy
the efficacy of such capabilities is
determined by top-down belief
propagation and bottom-up message
passing within and across organizational
layers or business units
um yeah so I think like that
optimization for like maybe information
or
um
I don't know like what are you
optimizing optimizing the connection
optimizing the flow of information
optimizing
um the link between up and downs like
like what are we really optimizing
four I don't know
yeah it's it's a little bit vague in how
he talks about it there's obviously
something I got kind of a little bit
frustrated with because like actually
building that top down bottoms up kind
of connective tissue is like a huge area
of research and there's like all these
like different
um approaches for it it's like a really
famous one is holocracy that I'm not
sure you guys are familiar with
holography hypocrisy he got famous
because it was implemented by by Zappos
uh to like mixed results potentially but
what a cool way that they do it is that
it's not like a very traditional pyramid
hierarchical structure but each like
subunit will kind of dynamically form
bonds with other levels of the hierarchy
kind of arbitrarily depending on needs
as they arise so like but they have a
whole system for how those uh those
bonds conform and how you generate links
across different levels of the hierarchy
and so that's just to say like this is
like a huge area of like research and
experimentation that no one really has
like a great answer for
um and yeah it's this is like a huge
huge open-ending questions
there's no General strategy for a bug
so it doesn't seem like there's going to
be a general organization chart or
communications platform
and technology is changing so rapidly
and intelligence augmentation this is
helping us like
sketch the first lines on our notebook
that takes us into a discussion and an
Adaptive process
and that is the reframing of the
strategy governance conversation it's
not this is the strategy Playbook
it's not the
um homework problems
but it's it's bringing some ideas to the
table that
are mixing it up
so like I don't know I think about
optimizing like sense making at each
level
um because of like the quote that's
stated here and so like how do you like
optimize sense making across layers like
it definitely has to do with like
information prioritization I think
um but but it's like how to selectively
choose like I guess it's like a very
open-ended question but I don't know
it's like I would like some concrete
examples it's something like I would
like to drill Bajan on like how have you
ever seen this done and like what worked
and what didn't
um for as far as optimizing like this
hierarchy flow
as to what is being optimized one
sort of capital maximalist approach is
like profit is to be maximized or risk
discounted profit or a triple bottom
line like there are imperatives for the
organization to optimize but that
doesn't mean that that becomes the
imperative at every communication step
and kind of the dream or direction of
informational free energy minimization
would be you'll be doing as good as you
can in the niche
from like a
energetics and Metabolism perspective
when you're informationally optimizing
if you're a bear making the best
possible decisions you will survive in
the niche
and so it's kind of like
recognizing the difference between the
ecological success of an organization or
or organism recognizing that that
embodied success and death isn't the
informational imperative
but for things that work and not things
that don't
fulfilling the informational imperative
should lead to the embodied success
because it's defined in that way
so it's easy to turn to like maximizing
profit as a firm objective but I think
that like that is short-sighted like I
definitely think that there's many other
things like if you're making the most
possible money of producing light bulbs
but right like so say I'm making a light
bulb and I'm like maximizing profit on
the light bulb and I'm I'm producing a
million of them for pennies right and
they're selling for you know ten dollars
each or whatever
um but I'm like polluting a river
because I'm making the light bulbs so
cheap like I'm not like adequately
disposing of waste or whatever then like
that's gonna have blowback like later
either through like EPA or through like
customers saying I don't want that
because it's not sustainable or whatever
so like if you're just exploitative or
yeah exploitative
um then it's not gonna work out in the
long run so like maximizing profit is a
very like delicate thing like especially
in terms of like company persistence and
sustainability like sustainability not
like an eco-friendly way but like
sustainability of the company itself
yeah I mean this oh sorry I just I was
thinking of fermenting bacteria
initially certain strategies work but
then that can lead to the production of
metabolites that that strategy will no
longer be optimal in so one has to
consider like externalities in the niche
and of course all of this is just a
statistical framework that's way before
we get into ethical imperatives or
preferences
yeah I mean so I think there's something
I think we covered in the the third live
stream but it's like okay how do you
how do you heard cats basically and get
all these different levels of the
organization to move in the same
direction and kind of balance that these
different things you might want to
optimize for that in the long term maybe
it goes for profit but you might have
like sub problems that you need to solve
that are not strictly profit and so one
of the most famous ways of doing this is
okrs so like objective key results and
so like at your top level of the
organization maybe it is profit or maybe
it is like some kind of double bottom
line but then as you go into like
subunits of the organization like say
you have customer service because your
customer service team is not optimizing
for profit they're optimizing for like a
customer experience or like csat for
example right and your legal team is not
optimizing for profit they have like
their own measure that they're they're
optimizing for the number of cases they
win or legal risk you know avoided I
don't know how you quantify that
um but there are ways that you can kind
of break the bigger the problem of
profit into sub problems uh and rather
than having you know everyone
going towards profit at the same time
all right oh so perfectly perfect segue
and so organizational uh sense making so
I'll read this organizational sense
making is not about optimally
approximating and objectively defined
external reality but developing and
enacting models of Reality by way of top
down bottom-up predictive coding
effectively the future arrives in the
present and becomes the Past Times time
moves at different rates in the brain's
hierarchy
as is true for the firm while time has
strictly no speed humans project speed
onto time as relations and interactions
increase in intensity and complexity
the firm's very existence is determined
by its curiosity field interaction with
its external environment fast at the
reflex low level I.E resource resource
markets and more slowly at higher
cognitive levels I.E strategic decision
making I mean this you know reminds me
of um like a paper that Daniel and I
have been working on and just how how
temporally active inference and fep
operates at different
um fast and slow
is
it kind of reminds me of how and pretty
much every company I think I've ever
worked at there's always this tendency
for the Bottom Rung of the organization
to think that the top round are just
like a bunch of like slow bumbling
idiots
there's like this temporal disconnect of
like the Bottom Rung of the organization
is giving feedback immediately and like
they're running little tiny experiments
every single day where they're getting
immediate feedback whereas like the top
wrong is like you know the board maybe
they're meeting quarterly and then they
have like some mandate and they don't
really get feedback synthesized to them
until like another three months uh and
so like there's always this tendency for
like there's always this temporal
disconnect and it always creates this
kind of like boundary or disconnect
between the bottom and top of the
organization
this point of time having no speed is
quite interesting we talk about oh it's
the food is taking it's too slow or
slower time scales faster time scales
longer distances
like it feels natural to talk about the
rate of speed
but even without going into
too much uh reconceptualizations of
speed it just isn't necessarily that way
and then in the brain as to like time
moves at different rates in the brain's
hierarchy
we could think about a neural firing
pattern
that takes place over some number of
milliseconds and then there's slower
waves and rhythms
they compose and they influence each
other they're all happening at once
technically it's all happening in the
same way at the same place the same
exact input outputs
but still it makes sense to talk about
some of these slower or larger waves and
some faster waves like in the EEG
rhythms
so
striking a balance between the
everything all at once real time
unfolding
and then these day week month year
decade nested time scales is a big part
of sense making
definitely okay habits of mind
um so I I liked this uh because I've
read good to great um the Jim Collins
book and when Tyler and I were first
starting out the series we talked about
like how that's very like leader-centric
and very like top down like the the
ideas that are presented in that book
um and so I I was like excited to see
this book uh good to Great to gone by
Alan werzel I have not um read it but he
talked about companies like I think
specifically like Circuit City is the
company right oh yeah it's here on the
cover of the book but Circuit City was
like one of the companies that uh Jim
Collins went through and good to great
and then now like there is no more
Circuit City and so he I guess kind of
outlines like the failings of like what
makes a good company a great company and
now like they're obsolete
um and maybe why they're Obsolete and so
he um outlines these habits of mind
um and I don't I haven't read the book
and I don't know enough but they're
listed here if you want to um read them
and maybe read the book
um but these habits of mind that are are
like necessary to
um stay relevant maybe
um so uh Bijan says that habits of mind
May equally explain why upper echelon is
generally resisting strategy process as
a matter of top top down bottom-up
prediction urbanization
um and he goes on to make the claim that
five out of where it's those 12 habits
of mind are foundational to prediction
processing framework fostering success
of strategic renewal
um and he briefly summarizes these
habits uh Tyler do you want to read
these scores did you find sure so first
one be humble run scared so continuously
doubt your understanding of things
business success contains the seeds of
its own destruction
two curiosity sustains the cat the world
is constantly changing be open and
curious and strive to learn from others
three evidence Trump's ideology and
business as in politics decisions are
too often based on unproven assumptions
about what works and what doesn't we all
need operating assumptions about human
nature the economy and the like but when
things do not work out as planned we
need to determine whether our
assumptions were based on evidence or
ideology four confront the brutal facts
the worst person you can fool is
yourself ignoring or denying reality
does not help it go away five chasing
possible dream do not be limited by the
tyranny of the war
foreign so I thought this was cool I
think a lot of these habits of mine
speak to the ability to like rewire the
playing while flying it
um I don't know like what what Bajan
stressed earlier in the chapter do you
guys have any um additional comments
here
um okay so another claim and this might
be who might be
oh yeah that's getting close to the end
okay Bichon says it is the circular
causality of belief belief propagation
message passing where prediction
processing Frameworks Effectiveness and
the organizational context most likely
breaks down neither the bottom-up
message passing nor the top-down belief
propagation are unobstructed we fail to
appreciate how organizational friction
which he defines as high levels of free
energy
compromised firm performance due to
First top-down enforced predictions and
prediction models that are not receptive
to bottom-up challenge second leak top
down bottom-up lateral generative
sensing and sense we can capabilities in
the form of error signaling and
processing and third poor communication
and absence of a language that is
suitable to level leverage prediction
processing framework for strategic
renewal
um so I thought that uh that was kind of
neat
um like how how the these are the faults
right
um and then he goes on to say
in the organizational context prediction
processing framework is determined by
three categorical imperatives and I've
abbreviated these kind of just
shortening them so that they fit on the
slide first upper echelon's prediction
models and corresponding predictions
must be explainable and explicitly
articulated and
um yeah so that goes into the
communication salience prioritization he
says the language of communications
layers are critical to Resource
configuration from performance and
eventually firm survival
um he also says each of the hierarchical
layers must have formal and informal
interfaces that couple each layer to the
next layer for a given hierarchical
structure of a firm to have any
legitimacy generative top-down bottom-up
sensing and sense making at every
hierarchical level should equally make
sense before an error message travels to
the next level it should not and cannot
be any bypassing of hierarchical layers
um I guess that's like don't go over
someone's head
um but also like yeah I I wonder like
about the bypassing about like the
information flow and the throughput and
how big does that channel have to be
um and lastly he says the firm's
generative model is the firm's Eco Niche
when we perceive the world as uncertain
and unpredictable it is a mere
reflection of the inadequacy of our
generative reality model
um so I think that that's how to avoid
the errors mentioned in in the previous
slide
any comments here final thoughts on the
material
one thought is I like number one where
he's talking about how you have to
articulate and communicate top down like
what your actual model is so it can be
challenged and something that I've
noticed is that oftentimes like people
will communicate their predictions but
not necessarily have those predictions
were generated or the components of that
like the components of the assumptions
that went into that prediction and that
makes it really hard for other levels of
the hierarchy to like even know what was
going on and what they should be
challenging at all and a lot of times
you'll just assume like okay like they
probably know what they're talking about
like they're the experts so like let's
just hope for the best
um but I really like that he said like
no you have to explicitly say what your
model is so it can be challenged
to the going over someone's head
on a previous slide it said
organizational friction is High free
energy we might want to finesse that by
saying relatively High free energy
because in general we're not interested
in the absolute value of a free energy
calculation but rather the gradients and
the direction at which we could act to
improve or increase it
so it's not about the total amount it's
about the relative amount so let's just
say it turned out that somebody from an
org chart perspective did go over their
head that could be understood as a
policy selection authorized or not
to structurally rewire the
communications architecture of the firm
now that rewiring
in a situation may be associated with a
decrease in organizational friction and
therefore a decrease in the free energy
so it may be an Adaptive decision
because no org chart is the final word
but that doesn't mean that every time
somebody tries to rewire the
communications architecture it would
decrease friction if people were just
getting all these side messages and
there'd be so many issues as well so
it's it's not to say to to do or not to
do it's giving the areas of
consideration the structure cognitive
and capacity oriented aspects
that we can have that ongoing
conversation and some principles that
help us
take selection and still do things in in
uncertain world with this little fun
caveat that the perception of the world
as uncertain and unpredictable is
actually an inadequacy of our generative
reality
yeah I mean even skipping different
levels of the hierarchy could be
something that you explicitly plan for
as well and build processes around so
for example I worked at a at a company
that they call it like the big red
button whereas if you were at the bottom
wrong in the organization and you saw
something that was going terribly wrong
wrong you could basically push this big
red button and it would file this like
report directly to the c-suite and would
skip all the levels and then they would
follow up with you directly and so like
they explicitly said like hey we know
that they're going to be things that are
shielded from our view and we want to
know about it and they build a process
explicitly around it
that so in terms oh sorry go ahead
Damian that reminds me of cells
signaling and then the ultimate red
button is like when the cellular
contents are spilling out it's like my
only message to share is that
I am no longer and all my insides are
like spilling onto you so it's like if
there's a protein that's usually
internal and it's being you're being
bathed in it
that's the red button that you needed so
yes that kind of emergency or a
conditional rewiring
maybe there's many patterns and motifs
where we might want to embed that kind
of flexibility into the communications
architecture so even though it is a
dynamic Communications architecture at a
higher level it's actually not changing
in its Dynamics like different people
are going to be in different video calls
but that doesn't mean that the
communications architectural plan is
changing it just means that difference
individuals are connected differently
so in terms of um sharing the model
Tyler like when you were talking about
um you know sharing how like the the top
level will share their predictions but
not necessarily how those predictions
were generated I'm like really reminded
of um academic research in which it's
like
I feel like everyone is so like shielded
from what's going on like you have the
principal investigator they like write a
grant the grant has like three specific
games it's just an example so then like
those three specific games the each grad
student will be working on one of the
Apes right or maybe they'll have a team
working on achieving one of the three
specific aims right and like these teams
are doing totally like work that they
think is totally unrelated like they
have no idea like the overarching
process of the grant like I wonder how
often like the pi shares like the entire
Grant with every student like I mean
that's not something that I typically
see and I think like that there's a lot
of shielding going on and I don't I
don't really know why like is it is it
like because it's just too much
information or because like they just
want the focus on to be on that one
thing like they want this the students
to have this myopic view or and I I just
understand you like what is your
experience there like do you think that
like pis generally share the entire
model or they just share a piece of it
like what is your experience and do you
think that that makes research
dysfunctional
interesting I've seen some
investigators who shared the grants or
other ongoing strategy documents or not
it reminds me of a computer program
like if you could perfectly isolate
every variable and for Loop and you can
really clearly say this is the scope of
this script and all of that
that may work in a computer system
but humans are always curious about the
context and the past and the future and
Alternate futures
so
that kind of strict information
encapsulation approach
might increase overhead decrease context
have to spend a lot of time
re-explaining things
it's not that one strategy is going to
be in general better than the other but
it seems like it could be a better
professional conversation if the lab
strategy governance were framed in a way
that accounting for people's differences
in like
familiarity with grant writing or with
experiment design
at least giving lob level awareness
doesn't seem like it'd be a bad thing
yeah there's an analogous problem within
a business organization and some of you
type like okr is where you take it like
this big goal you had like let's say
it's growth and you split up into
subcomponent parts so one problem I've
had in one organization actually
multiple organizations is on the growth
funnel so like how you get leads and
then how you convert them into like
actual conversions and sales right and
so this what often happens is that
there's a trade-off between getting more
leads and the quality of those leads and
so what you'll do is you'll have like a
top level growth initiative like we have
to grow by 10 and then you're like cool
like marketing people increase your
leads and then uh product people all
right increase the conversion on this
funnel so but what actually happens
though is if the marketing team
increases their leads they often get
more poor quality leads like you're
dipping into like lower quality Elites
increase your leads and so that actually
reduces the conversion of the next step
of the funnel and so like they're both
narrowly optimized on like their one
little piece of the puzzle but they
actually really directly impact each
each other and then you get into these
like really painful conversations
between your your marketing team and
your your growth product team which is
like really like if they were just had
this like more holistic view to begin
with like no we're just trying to grow
guys like that's what we're trying to do
like we don't care about your little
piece of the puzzle and so like there's
often this time where like by breaking
things off too narrowly uh you really
missed a bigger picture and this is
super super common
yeah
the last we'll have it having the um the
apriori partitioning
means that you are saying like uh
not even the structure of the problem is
going to change again if you only have
to partition the problem one time then
maybe it can be cut and dry
but those kinds of dependencies
are why we need uh these kinds of
composable
partitioning strategies
so that different parts of a base graph
can be identified because
we're looking at a lot of text but all
of these Notions of a generative model
generative process
we can also see that kind of a base
graph representation in the background
especially as these types of
perspectives move closer to application
awesome well that's the end of the
content here for chapter six we will
delve into chapter 7 next week unless
you guys have any final things to say
um that's it for me so thanks for for
being here and I'm looking forward to
carrying on pushing forward learning
more about free energy governance and
future discussions with the author
thank you
all right thank you until next time
bye